Literally nothing good will come of a of
an actual war between India and Pakistan
because the Pakistanis will lose. Mhm.
It's as simple as that. They'll lose.
And I'm not talking about nuclear
weapons. I'm talking just about a
conventional war. That the Pentagon
controlled the Pakistani nuclear
arsenal.
The Pakistanis have come out publicly
and said that they control the nukes,
but I can tell you definitively
Mhm. that
the State Department was telling both
sides, "If you're going to fight, fight.
Keep it short and keep it non-nuclear."
If nuclear weapons are introduced, the
whole world is going to change. And so I
think there was restraint on both sides.
The Pakistanis need to come to a policy
conclusion that there's nothing positive
for them in fighting India. Nothing.
Literally nothing good will come of a of
an actual war between India and Pakistan
because the Pakistanis will lose. Mhm.
It's as simple as that. They'll lose.
And I'm not talking about nuclear
weapons. I'm talking just about a
conventional war. The Pakistanis will
lose.
Right. And so there's no benefit to
constantly provoking the Indians.
At the CIA, we called the Indian policy
um strategic patience.
The the Indian government would have
been perfectly within its rights to
respond respond by striking Pakistan,
and they didn't.
And I remember at the White House people
were saying, "Wow, the Indians are
really exhibiting a very mature foreign
policy here. We expected the Indians to
to strike back."
And they didn't.
And that kept the the world from what
might have been a nuclear exchange.
Right. But India's gotten to the point
where
they can't risk strategic patience being
misunderstood as weakness.
And so they had to respond.
Right.
>> Now the question the question now that
CIA analysts are likely asking
themselves
are did the Pakistanis learn their
lesson
not to keep poking the hornet's nest and
expecting to not be stung. When I was
when I was stationed in Pakistan in
2002, I was told unofficially that
that the Pentagon controlled the
Pakistani nuclear arsenal. That
Musharraf had turned control over to the
United States because he was afraid of
exactly what you just described.
But the Pakistanis in the intervening
years, and remember I was there 23
years ago,
over the last 23 years, the Pakistanis
have come to say that is absolutely not
true.
The United States has nothing to do with
the Pakistani nuclear arsenal. That
Pakistani generals are the ones that
control it.
So I don't know if if that's true,
then I would be very worried about who
is in charge politically in Pakistan.
Well, You know, for example for example
um
Imran Khan. I can't believe that I
forgot his name. Who's in jail? A
popular leader.
>> jail? Yes, yeah. Right. And still wildly
popular. Wildly, yeah.
He told us when he was still the prime
minister, he said, "Listen, I've got
this political situation here
domestically. I'm going to start blaming
you for everything."
And and the ambassador laughed and said,
"We get blamed for everything anyway, so
we don't care."
So everything that happened, it was the
United States' fault. And it was the US
they turned their backs on us, and the
US did this, and the US did that. And
then they arrested him anyway.
So he got a message out to the US
government saying, "Can you help me get
out of this?"
And we went to Jemima Goldsmith, his
gold whatever her name wife ex-wife.
And she went to Pakistan and asked them
if they would release him. And they
said, "No."
So like you, I'm worried about continued
disagreement in Pakistani politics that
has the potential to spill into the
streets because the Pakistanis have a
tendency to get themselves spun up. Mhm.
And people die during demonstrations,
and there are attacks against political
figures, and assassinations, and
and uh and the country is not known for
its uh transformative, you know, leaders
making positive decisions.
[Music]